hello um so thanks for having me um I
want to tell you the incredible work
that the three teams you see on the
screen here we had the Voyer flight team
and anomaly team that helped us resolve
the anomaly that happened on the flight
data subsystem and the deep space
Network which is the set of antennas we
use to track our spacecraft um the
biggest question you may have is what's
a mission assurance manager so I have
the best job in the whole world whenever
anything goes wrong with an instrument
or a spacecraft I get to jump in and
help solve the problem and additionally
I'm kind of the independent reviewer um
you can all imagine back when you were
younger you'd get together with your
friends you have this great idea and it
would go terribly wrong well that
happens to engineers and professionals
at all levels and so that's my job is to
be the adult in the room and make sure
we don't have
issues so to get started I want to tell
you a little bit about the mission so
you understand why it's so important to
us and it is very important to us so the
voyagers launched in
1977 and they were designed to explore
the outer planet specifically Jupiter
and Saturn of course they got to all
four of them Voyer 2 doing Uranus and
Neptune and that changed the way we
thought about the solar system utterly
changed planetary science after that in
the 1990s we became a he spheric mission
the he sphere is a magnetic bubble that
surrounds the Sun and we're in the heos
spere it's actually very far far out
even Beyond planet's orbits and the idea
here was that Voyer would move out
Beyond these planets sample the outer
heliosphere and then perhaps make it
Interstellar space because nobody knew
there was a huos spere boundary nobody
knew how far it was and so that was our
new goal in 1990 today we've crossed
that boundary as you'll see and we're
actually in innerstellar space and I
think this may be our most important
data set that we ever collect because
nobody's going to be here again for
decades perhaps longer um these two
spacecraft are deep in their exposive
space giving us information that's
critically important why because as you
can see in the upper corner there other
stars have you heliosphere as well
they're called astrospheres so an
astronomer can collect those photons and
make an interpretation what they're
seeing but it's really valuable to have
the actual understanding of what that
inner Stiller space might be like that
those shock waves are interacting with
so it gives astronomers ground truth in
terms of interpreting things like this
the other um the other thing you can see
here is that this is some data from one
of our instruments this is the plasma
wave subsystem um what it does is it
collects electromagnetic uh information
frequencies Against Time which we heard
about earlier today um the PWS actually
collects plasma waves plasmas are ions
and electrons that are um embedded in a
magnetic field when that situation
happens those particles will exhibit
wavelike characteristics so this
instrument's designed to find those all
these dark splotches are actually uh the
what happens when a when a corono mass
injection the things that cause Roars on
Earth those propagate out for years and
when they hit the Helia sphere they
actually ring into Interstellar space so
Voyer was hearing the the eruptions from
the Sun even outside the helipa which
was very cool nobody really expected
that and you can see this uh a very line
there's a thin line that goes out uh
that thin line represents the primary
plasma frequency and that gives us
density so this is just one example the
amazing um science that these
instruments are still
providing oh excuse me so this is a a uh
map of essentially where we were and
where we are this is astronomical units
on the the x-axis on the bottom
astronomic unit is a distance between
the Earth and the Sun or about eight
light minutes uh you can see we're well
out there out from the Sun and uh this
is the ecliptic latitude in other words
how far north and south we are if you
look down at the tiles you can imagine
one of those is an au Voyer one is about
as far away as this patio is across so
and the distance between Earth and Mars
is about that far so you can see the
voyers are extremely far
away oh actually you'll see the uh blue
boundary there is also where we crossed
into the inner Stellar space so it was
much further out than most astronomers
thought so these are our instruments uh
we have a magnetometer we have the
plasma wave subsystem um they're mounted
they use these antennas the
magnetometers are on a boom to keep them
was in the spacecraft the PWS uses these
whip antennas this is a 13 M boom so
these are not little spacecraft this is
a three uh 3 meter across hyen antenna
um and then we have some particle
instruments we have the cosmic ray
subsystem looking at high energy
particles and then a couple of plasma
instruments so those are our spacecraft
and the instruments that are still
active
so let's talk about our spacecraft
status so we are 15 billion miles away
for Voyager one I'm going to talk mostly
about Voyer one because that's what
we're here to talk about our Li time is
22 and a half hours one way in other
words that's how long it takes to stick
of the command to our spacecraft to get
a roundtrip response it's 45 hours so
basically we get contact with our
spacecraft after we do something two
days later um this uh diagram in the
upper corner there shows you Voyer one
and Voyer 2 Crossing outside the
heliopause it's another graphic um I
like it because it shows that we're
actually moving out through the nose of
the heliopause in other words just by
dumb luck we ended up leaving the solar
system in the direction the sun was
going so the voyagers are no longer
gravitationally bound of the sun they're
actually orbiting the center of the
Galaxy and they have a 230 million year
period so they're moving about uh 3 Au
per year faster than the solar
system so imagine a candle
um you can see the light from it you can
feel the heat so all that energy if you
collect it then take that and divide it
by six so 1 six of a candle that's 13
watts of energy so a 70 M station the
large dish will run the far far right uh
that station 70 M across can detect that
signal and pull 160 bits per second out
of it three 34 met stations that we
array together they can also perform
that feed so that's essentially how we
collect data the spacecraft are always
broadcasting we can track it as often we
can get these antennas um we can
actually go up to 1.2 kilobits per
second and that's how we get that data I
showed you earlier it's recorded on our
fancy digital tape craft recorder it's
an eight track and it's still reog grade
um that's uh that data comes down only
when we can array all the stations so
this picture happened earlier this year
this the first time we array all six
antennas we usually have only five in
the array so we're uh we're working to
to try and get more and more antennas
because we're getting out near the limit
of This 1.2 kilobits per
second excuse me we don't have a safe
mode many spacecraft play it safe when
something goes wrong they kind of shut
things down and stop doing things Voyer
one just resets its processors picks up
the pieces and goes it has very robust
wall protection very aggressive we have
94 years of experience with our flight
systems between the two spacecraft we
have about 12 people working on
spacecraft now so there many of them are
part-time that's a lot of spacecraft for
very few on a
people and then our big our big problem
that we're dealing with is power and
thermal these days so we launched with
uh enough plutonium to power the
spacecraft it has a half-life of about
88 years this is a picture of the fuel
clads when they're fresh they glow red
hot um they're embedded in in little
cans that stick off Voyager and there's
thermac couples around them they
generate electricity based on the heat
difference between the interior and the
exterior um we're down to about as much
power as a box fan or a rice cooker at
this point for those big spacecraft
which is pretty incredible we also just
started operating them with unregulated
voltages because we realized we could
turn we could go off the voltage
regulator and keep our instruments
powered which is the the reason we're
there and um that was kind of a scary
moment for us but it worked well so so
far so good generally we have to take
action within a year or less all the
time because of our power and thermal
constraints the less power we have of
course we risk undervolting our
spacecraft and power is also dissipated
so we have thermal issues we may freeze
our roll lines we'll talk about that a
little
more this is a functional block diagram
of our spacecraft um you can see Voyer
one looks pretty darn good red is things
that are failed and black are things
that are powered off because power and
then we have a few gold items that are
just degraded subsystems so I think we
all wish our our appliances worked this
well after 47 years um I'll PL out this
uh right here this is the flight data
subsystem we're going to be talking a
lot about that you'll notice there's a
very thin line going down into the toet
modulation unit and then down into the
uh the radio subsystem down there so
this is the path we're going to talk
about the path from the flight data
computer to the temp modulation unit to
the
radio um just quickly um speaking of
things that are wrong to keep our
spacecraft operating uh we have to make
changes all the time and it's getting
more and more frequent back in the early
part of the last decade um it was not a
big deal we had things happen
occasionally that we had to adjust to
more and more now we're having to take
steps to either keep from losing an
instrument avoid degradation or actually
we prevent the loss of our spacecraft so
it's getting tougher to fly these with
our small
Team all right this is what you guys
came to he computers in the anomaly so
we have three very cool computers on the
Voyer spacecraft and they're two of each
type for redundancy um these are
Humanity's oldest continuous
continuously operating computers so I
think it's important to remember that is
as you hear about them these are the
first reprogrammable de deep space
flight computers they operate without
microprocessors and each has its own
unique GPL constructed Assembly Language
so the CCs is basically responsible for
issuing commands to the spacecraft it's
a viking machine essentially the Viking
Landers and orbiters used a computer of
this type and it's an 18-bit interrupt
driven processor um constructed out of
transistors it's TTL logic we actually
use some RC Logic on some of our
subsystems but this is a fancy TTL
machine and it has nine or 4,000 words
of plated wire memory um if you don't
know what that is you can look it up in
the internet but it reminds you of
Rebecca's talk and the uh the weaving
it's essentially a set of wires and you
store data on them by putting a small
magnetic field into the wires and it
works great after all these years um our
attitude control subsystem it is used to
control the attitude and pointing of our
spacecraft it's a very similar machine
um it uh it has an extra board that they
used to make sure that there was enough
speed to manage the attitude of the
spacecraft these two are basically alike
Voyer on on the the command computer
system we actually use both processors
because we're short on memory so finally
the one that matters to us is over on
the far side that's the fds so this was
added because during the planning for
the mission they realized that when when
Voyager flew through a planetary system
it was going to overwhelm the spacecraft
data system all this data coming in and
under a day essentially um they didn't
think these computers could handle it so
they built a seos machine and uh it has
8,000 words of memory and um this was
put on board basically to make sure that
we could process all that data this is a
very important computer for us because
it uh basically commands the instruments
it coets and formats all of our science
and engineering Telemetry and it
provides all of our timing
information so what happened and how did
we figure it
out so back in November of last year we
had a normal pass come up but we had no
Telemetry so Telemetry is basically
processed by taking looking for a frame
marker saying this is a packet of data
and we're going to decode it and look at
what it says um we were not getting
those frame markers and um the only good
thing was we had a carrier signal
otherwise we' have been really scared so
we could see this the carrier but it was
not being modulated so our deep space
tracking Network all those antennas they
worked for several days and they
determined that we were seeing a
constant frams of zero and one symbols
and um there were no Toom Fame markers
whatsoever so the result here was that
we had no visibility on our spacecraft
Voyager will will drift back and forth
based on sun position and we can see
that slight signal variation from over a
few hours uh we could see that our radio
frequencies were per predict and we see
in the next few days we could see we
could command our spacecraft but that
was it uh somebody on our team pointed
out this is kind of like having your
monitor broken and having to find out
where your cursor is to fix the monitor
so not a very good situation for us so
we formed an anomaly team this was about
another dozen people that were brought
in who are specialists in various
disciplines to help us out which is kind
of the way JPL does these
things so new initially we realized it
we had to be the fds the tmu or the
radio frequency subsystem after a little
work
and we changed the frequency this is an
example by commanding the tmu and the
RFS but occasionally it didn't work
which was puzzling we also had What's
called the open loop recorder which is
essentially using the DSN instead of
collect data like a radio telescope and
what happened was we could see that we
were getting these modulations which
told us the clock signal was working
because the speed was about right so we
knew that pieces were working across the
the set of three subsystems but we
weren't sure what was wrong yet so we we
pretty much focused on the
fds um based on the fact that we were
getting these kinds of Transitions and
the fds wasn't doing much in response to
our commands so our top priority was to
figure out what the FTS was and how it
worked because unfortunately the person
who was the real expert had retired
decades ago and the person who was their
fill in their backup had retired two
years ago so it was the worst place it
could have hit
us so these are some examples of some of
the documentation we dug up on the fds
and I hope you guys can see them that's
good because we couldn't read
those so they're all handwritten uh the
one up on the upper left has got some
handwriting these are very dim circuit
diagrams and these are handwritten
timelines for how to change fds
processors so this was um we were lucky
to find these some things we couldn't
find a lot of it was like this that had
been scanned and frequently these
sources were contradictory ambiguous why
because we changed the way the
spacecraft worked with every planetary
encounter and entering the vim and when
things broke so there was a lot of
opportunity for ambiguity to arise in
the documents over the course of 50
years this is my favorite example so
this is a page out of an important fds
document the change bar on the far side
indicates it's a change but somebody
went in and made the very cryptic Circle
the sentence and cross it out and I have
no idea to this day what it means I have
no idea um maybe it was important maybe
they crossed it out because they thought
Crossing out was important I'm not sure
so there was other cases like this so we
were even so confused in some cases we
weren't sure if we were sending data to
the fds should it be least significant
bit first or most significant bit first
we had that level of uncertainty so the
only thing we could do is dig in and
research more and debate so we had a lot
of debates between our flight team and
the Tigra team trying to figure out what
the best thing to do but ultimately we
just had to kind of suck it up and guess
at some point and we made the right
guesses which is good so let me go a
little deeper into the FTS so you can
understand what we were dealing with um
at the
top I'm just going to take this out at
the top we have memory a memory B failed
back in 1981 this is the processor the
processor runs the flight software
that's embedded on memory this is I
can't read this this is how you command
the fds this is the state vector control
unit which basically manages the
Redundant units you see here so if you
want to change redundancy you use this
box this is our oscillator and timing
change this is engineering IO science IO
tape recorder IO uh modulation IO and
then our encoders and then we have
triply redundant power supplies because
this is volatile memory
so um a lot of things to look at there
so what we had to do is pick what was
most likely to be causing the problem we
were seeing and balance that against
what was the most risky thing we could
or the least risky thing we we could be
doing some of these we didn't want to
play with because we just did not want
to switch those components because of
the risk involved so it was always a
balancing TR act the other thing that
happened was this kind of fell into a
weekly schedule because we had to wait
two days for our downlinks so basically
what we' do is what you see there we'd
observe we' design our next test we'd
build the commands radiate them wait two
days and then observe the
results so this really was playing 20
questions with the
spacecraft um what happened was we we
came up with this set of things we were
going to do and um each one represented
a risk benefit trade if any of these had
come out positively we would have
stopped right because we would have had
an answer for what it was this is like
playing 20 questions and always getting
no for your answer no matter what we
tried the only good thing was is it let
us knock out things that it would not be
so if we swapped out the oscillator and
timing chain we would say well it's not
that obviously ly and hope that we
unscrewed something else up on the
instrument so this is a fishbone fa tree
um you don't have to read it don't worry
the important thing is is that there are
the brown things are things that we
ruled out and across the top we have
Mission operations issues um basically
ground stuff we have safing algorithms
on the spacecraft that might have might
have uh tried to change a configuration
we have a lot of Telecom stuff and then
at the bottom we have all the fds pieces
we knocked all these out without any
telemetry
by by debate or by trying something like
that this is the fds in the same type of
a diagram so again everything Brown has
been eliminated and you can see at the
top we took out the MDS we took out the
uh State vector control and some of the
other iOS there on the side at the
bottom we took out State vector control
and timing um we took out commanding and
the power um in the next to last and
over in The Far Side we took out the
radio stuff again this was either debate
on the ground trying to Swatch swap a
component and seeing if we fixed the
problem or not so without Telemetry this
is pretty darn good and you can see we
were left with basically just the fds
memory or the flight software and
processor potentially was there but we
were too scared to touch the processor
so we just kind of said you know it's
probably working because we're getting
timing signals
out very good so that took us three
months and then we arrived at this the
fds is broken so we had narrowed it down
to that and we finally figured out why
our Telecom commands weren't working
some of the time it turns out that the
team had built some of those as
contingency commands using something
called seconds mode which uses the clock
to trigger the commands most of the time
we use frame mode so it turns out that
only the frame commands were the ones
that weren't working so this told us
even though we'd forgotten this fact we
figured it out and it told us that the
FTS wasn't giving us frames this really
put the nail in the coffin that we
understood what the issue was
so I'm going to put a couple of names
out here David Cummings at JPL was kind
of one of the heroes Arman Arslanian was
the other um David figured out how the
FTS code work because nobody knew how to
do it we have data mode so data mode is
just a different speed of data return
it's like a different modem setting
essentially so we had 10 different modes
only four of those used today and the
idea behind them is they each collect
package and Route data from the fds to
the teamu and then the aana and that's
that's the way you work if you have to
you want a different mode to playback
data from the tape recorder versus
sending the real-time data versus just
sending engineering data so each of
those modes can be thought of as a
program or at least that's how David
thought of them and the problem was we
couldn't start or change these programs
now underneath those data mode programs
there's the P tables and these are code
groupings of sub routines that are
useful they're collected they tend to
have the same uh fun same similar
functions but they're slightly different
algorithms and then under the p P tables
there's yet another layer of code so a
given data mode might use code from
different PES and what we really had to
do is get our for data mode uh
reestablished so David asked the key
question if code execution was somehow
stuck on a p table how could we unstick
it and we thought that was the most
likely case because commands just
weren't having an impact so it turns out
there's two variables mode which is uh
what you command from the ground and C
mode which the software sets and these
determine what a data mode you're in and
these just flat weren't working we
thought so we decided to use Hardware
pokes instead of using a a nice safe
method where you tell the processor
please write this data to this location
we're just saying here's some data put
it in that address and these are
dangerous we've lost uh we lost Viking
one we lost Mars Global surveyor to
Hardware pokes so we don't like to use
them we' never used them in Voyager but
in this case we deemed it the safest way
to proceed so we built 20 pokes so both
variables for each of the 10 modes and
we link that on March 1st and it didn't
look very
promising but the DSN was uh was using
the olr and what this is what they saw
this is residual subcarrier plot on the
bottom on the far side there and where
the two lines are very fixed that's our
dial tone right that's the zeros and
ones as it looks in this this type of
plot you can see that when we sent the
other uh some set some of the variables
we got a response which was the first
time we'd seen the FTS do anything in 4
months so this was pretty exciting
um we left it in that one you can see
there at the end where it was sending
something down um and this told us the
processor responded number one it told
us memory was sound and it told us that
this was likely a memory corruption um
now since we weren't producing Telemetry
markers we couldn't read this as
Telemetry this is just stuff coming down
so the DSN it's worth a paper in itself
the DSN figured out this amazing way to
decode this data and give us what the
data
represented and it turns out it
represented something really cool um
this was an accidental memory duve
unbelievably so the processor we left it
in that mode somehow it's a direct
memory access machine somehow it just
said I'm going to read memory and it was
sending us memory dunk completely free
um so it was we basically could say the
whole memory and we noticed immediately
that there were 256 contiguous words
1400 to 14 FF that were corrupted or had
the potentially be corrupted and these
were all unfortunately in that layer of
code under the P tables so these are
routines that are used by every every
piece of the fds basically um and then
additionally one of our Engineers
determined the next day that this was a
single Ram chip in the FTS that is
responsible for the fifth bit in each
address location so we understood what
was going on so this is kind of
cool I got permission to actually show
you assembly this is the address then
this is the actual code that's supposed
to be there if the the word doesn't have
yellow then it should have one in the
fifth bit but if it's supposed to be
zero you can see everything's off by a
bit these are the labels in the assembly
this is the actual op codes it looks
kind of like 885 processor and then this
is uh the data associated with it and
then the comments so that's what
assembly looks
like for the fds and Voyager and each
computer has a different Assembly
Language so now the hard part how do you
fix that took us three months to figure
out what was wrong
so we had three priorities because we
didn't have toet we didn't have any
memory one was demonstrate we could
control the processor again two is get
engineering back because that would tell
us our spacecraft was healthy and
finally we don't have a mission if we
can't get science back so the real issue
here was the 1990s memory constraint
they loaded up this special version it
was code that just went everywhere
because you have those layers of code
and they wanted to reuse everything with
only 8,000 words you reuse every snippet
of code you can so the code just jumped
constantly all over the place um
additionally our flight team had never
buil a load this big and this was a new
process using these Hardware pokes so
our flight team had to do a lot of extra
work
too so earlier when all that
investigative work was going on we found
some object code and it turned out this
was a program called minum rot that had
not been used in 35 years and uh it it
actually does this small amount of
framed clock Terry sending it back to
the ground and it's framed which was
exciting for us and um we thought that
would be our good hell World program and
additionally they took M minm rot and
they morphed it this is where Arman
began to help out they morphed it into a
program that would use that same framing
but give us an mro so in prep we told
the fds to not generate frames because
we didn't want the processor to wake up
and begin issuing commanding that was on
board and loaded on our spacecraft so we
turned off frames we upin and linked
minum Rod that means we set uh we loaded
the program and we put the pointer at
zero where minum rot loads that's how we
link and it actually worked um we got
Telemetry using this uh we had a custom
tool that they developed for us again
and then we sent meno the next week and
that worked as well so so far so good we
had the processor under
control next we had to repair the codes
this is 256 instructions that had to be
relocated we had to preserve the
behavior of course to get our data back
but tying was key because anytime we
added a step to do these extra jumps it
would play with the timing of the
program which could kill us so we
understood we had to be super careful
with the timing so the last the only
benefit we had was that we were
cannibalizing one of these obsolete data
modes we had now the challenges these
guys faced were incredible we didn't
know that we had the right instruction
set I showed you in the instruction set
there we didn't know that was the one
that was used to build the software back
when there was an assembler we didn't
know that the source code version was
the same as what was running on board to
spacecraft we had a listing of the code
but but it was a Microsoft Word document
it was optical character recognition
scan so we didn't know if there were
errors in it um we have no assembler so
they're they're just playing with bits
there's no simulator and there's no test
bed so there were a few challenges I so
basically this was bar bar knuckle
binary
manipulation and they had to think of
all the problems I'm sure you guys are
far better than I am at thinking the
problems associated with with playing
with memory like this you could override
something you can fail to recognize
jumps you how do you debug it and fly on
a flying spacecraft and how do you know
you're not missing something in those
instruction sets and codes and the list
goes on and on so what they did is they
took every possible thing that could go
wrong they made a list and then they
iterated their code adjustments with
that list with multiple people and that
was essentially how they came with these
patches um and we said that was okay
because we
were we said that was okay because we're
effectively no Telemetry without that
and frankly how bad could things get
worse than they were so we uploaded this
and linked it on April 20th and this was
a big day we got Telemetry coming down
for the first time this is uh Armen in
the blue and David in the green and then
this is our flight team our tiny little
Flight Team celebrating so that was a
good
day but we weren't done yet so now we
have to get the science back and we were
worried because it took a lot of code to
get one mode back now we have three it
turns out it wasn't that bad the code
reuse was was pretty amable to what they
done but we did have some other problems
um again we were out of space we used it
all up the engineering high rate memory
that we were cannibalizing it was gone
so we found an old Memo from the 1980s
that mentioned free memory we looked at
the memory readouts and it looked like
it was just not being used so we assumed
it was free and went with that um this
was an upper memory and it wasn't in
right protected region of memory which
is a concern because we'd like it to be
right protected but if we went to lower
memory it takes an extra step to go
between high and low memory so we were
worried about the timing applications
again so we ate the risk that we were
writing to unwrite protected memory and
we patched it on May 18th and it worked
as well so I want to kind of highlight
that one because I keep saying this
little statement like it's really easy
these guys did four patches we uplinked
them but I want to show you just how
hard it was what they
did so this is a map along the bottom
it's zero to 255 words trust me and then
the next row up that's kind of slanted
you'll just keep counting up right these
are addresses incrementing along there
this is upper memory 4,000 to 8,000 so
this is essentially a memory map an
Excel this blue line going across this
is the the failed chip so all these
locations were trashed we didn't need
the little piece that's called copy in
the middle there but all the rest of
this had to be relocated you can see
that they took some of the sub routines
and they broke them into pieces they
stuffed them anywhere they could find in
space all over the memory this is all
upper memory they put in 14 14 different
specific uh relocations of code in this
case to recover the functionality that
was lost in the blue line additionally
this is now from 0 to 8,000 addresses
and 100 addresses across these are all
of the new and modified instructions
that they had to do they had the change
to to reference this relocated code
again no assembler no test bed no
simulator these guys were
awesome then finally we had to restore
our spacecraft and instruments so um we
got our frames turned back on we had to
resync our cxs we got the autonomous
sequencing roughly going we're still
playing with that because things got
pretty screwed up and three of the four
instruments that stopped working
properly because the fds is kind of
their caretaker and one of them has this
little motor the the upper half of this
instrument rotates 180° in 8 discreet
steps every uh 2 minutes or so it's
stepped over 8 million times in Flight
it got stuck during this downtime so we
we reinitialized the instrument and it
looked pretty bad for a while and then
little by little it broke itself free
and began to work again which was really
good news for us so basically at the end
of May we were back to nominal
operations and then we had uh two data
modes for the PWS to play back and
record and those were confirmed in July
and that's how you fix your 47y old
computer from 15 billion miles
away that was pretty
cool and just you know I didn't do that
that was the that was David and Arman
they were amazing so um I'm not going to
go over this whole slide because some of
this is internal but um I just gave this
talk Thursday for the first time so you
guys are the first people outside of JPL
to hear it um I think the voyagers give
this beautiful balance in their software
between operational flexibility balanced
against understandability and intrinsic
robustness in other words Voyer software
is understandable it can recover from
almost anything but it's also flexible
and that's a hard balance I think
nowadays most of the spacecraft I work
on you can't tell what the software is
going to do because you have competing
algorithms you have so many so many
possible triggers for called actions
that you can't anticipate them in
simulators so I've seen cases where we
get algorithms fighting it out over
battery control or something like that
and you just can't figure out even the
experts can't figure out what they're
doing we could figure out with what
Voyer was doing even without Telemetry
um I think the negative that really hurt
us was our spacecraft have been healthy
for decades and that uh that certainly
contributes to loss of knowledge um and
then I think um we talked a little bit
about um Fabric and maintaining data you
guys thought lost in accessible
documentation voyager's been through so
many media transitions right paper
through scanning through CD discs
through tape drives through we used
paper tape um and cards at the beginning
our some of our ground software was was
basically on a Unix system but it's
emulating a water cooled univac from the
1970s um all this stuff is is evolving
constantly in over a 50-year mission we
didn't have the money to maintain it so
we got got into the situation where the
documentation was bad so I agree that's
a really difficult problem and we need
to do a little better with that um but
we do have some final Bulls we're we're
dealing with some of these um issues we
had because we want to get out to around
200 Au which would be in uh let's see
2035 I don't know if we will get there
um so the gray boxes are are years the
gold numbers underneath them are the
actual Aus were away these bars with
lecp CRS Megan PWS that's when the
instruments get turned off they've
already been on about six years longer
than we thought we need we would have to
turn them off because of the changes
we've made um these little covered boxes
if I take one of those away this
timeline shrinks by that amount these
are all steps that we take to increase
the timeline so our goal is to keep them
alive until 20 2030s something like that
but you can see that I've got an
estimated survival probability there in
the light pink um the probability of us
making Beyond 2028 begins to drop pretty
quickly so we've got at least four or
five more years in them I think we're
also having some Thruster issues that
may be the end we're going to do a
Thruster Branch swap in the next two
weeks so keep your fingers
crossed and then last we are an
inspiration Mission this uh this really
taught us that we matter to and inspire
people around the world our project
manager Susie DOD calls these Humanity
spacecraft because people do care about
them we had universally positive and
supportive media coverage during the an
aloy which is pretty rare these days for
any event we had 90 significant media
hits hundreds of Internet stories on our
website was the big story of the year
and we had social media um mentions and
and benchmarks way above average but
best of all we get really cool fan mail
so Dana
[Applause]